High Commissioner for Germany. Women's Affairs Branch Records, 1949-1985
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
High Commissioner for Germany. Women's Affairs Branch Records
1949-1985
United States. Office of High Commissioner for Germany. Women's Affairs Branch
MS 368
2 boxes (1.6 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
International organization. In 1949, the Office of the United States sent a Women's Affairs Specialist to Germany to assist in organizing associations for German women. The records document efforts to promote women's participation in the public sphere of postwar Germany. The papers include official correspondence of the National Office, the Women's Affairs Branch, the Council of Hessian Women's Organizations, and the Buero fuer Staatsbuergerliche Frauenarbeit of the Regional Branch in Hessen.
Historical Note
In 1949, the H.I.C.O.G. sent Betsy Knapp of the League of Women Voters as their Women's Affairs Specialist to Germany to assist in organizing travel to the U.S. for German women. In addition, her responsibility included targeting women's organizations for Marshall Plan funding. With Knapp as their American consultant, the Buero fuer Frauenfragen was created in 1949-50 under the directorship of Antje Lemke-Bultmann. The funding for the first year (1951) came predominantly from the U.S. By the end of 1952, the U.S. was pressing the organization to seek its funding in Germany. Ursula Gaertner, a delegate from the German government, was able to secure resources for that year. At the end of 1952, the organization realized that in order to increase their constituency, they needed to broaden their platform, and the Buero fuer Staatsbuergerliche Frauenarbeit was created in early 1953. Furthermore, they combined their efforts with the Council of Hessian Women's Organizations to counsel approximately 16 women's organizations. Their purpose was to span from voter registration to foreign affairs, to the promotion of women in politics and public affairs. Erna Schlepper replaced Antje Lemke-Bultmann as the director of the Buero in 1954.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
These are records of the Women's Affairs Specialist of the H.I.C.O.G. and affiliated women's organizations in the Federal Republic of Germany. The collection has printed materials and official correspondence of the H.I.C.O.G.'s National Office, the Women's Affairs Branch, the Council of Hessian Women's Organizations, and the Buero fuer Staatsbuergerliche Frauenarbeit of the Regional Branch in Hessen. The records document these organizations' efforts to promote women's participation in the public sphere of postwar Germany. There are scattered reports for each of the organizations from 1949 to 1985.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into two series:
I. National Office
II. Regional Branch (Hessen)
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The records are open to research according to the rules and regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
These records were received from Betsy Knapp in three installments between 1985 and 1987. An earlier group of records was consolidated with this gift.
Search Terms
Women--Germany (West)--History--Sources; Women--International cooperation--History--20th century--Sources; United States. Office of High Commissioner for Germany. Women's Affairs Branch
- SERIES I NATIONAL OFFICE
  - U.S Specialist Reports, 1950-52 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Visiting Experts Series Reports, 1951-52 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - International Women's Conference, Bad Reichenall, F.R.G., 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - International Young Women's Conference, Hindelang, F.R.G., 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Women in West Germany, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- SERIES II REGIONAL BRANCH (HESSEN)
  - Women's Affairs Branch (Hessen)
    - Monthly Reports, 1949-52 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Summaries and evaluations, 1951-72 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Frau in der Gemeinde," Haus Schwalbach (course material), 1951-58 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Domestic law in the F.R.G.: publications, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Betsy Knapp: correspondence, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Betsy Knapp: correspondence about her visit to the Federal Republic of Germany, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 11a)
    - Hetty Schmitt-Maas: clippings, obituary, 1982-83 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Council of Hessian Women's Organizations
    - Reports, pamphlets, 1951-56 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Buero fuer Staatsbuergerliche Frauenarbeit
    - Reports: agendas, budget, summaries, 1950-75 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Thirty-year anniversary, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Erna Schlepper: clippings, obituary, 1982-85 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Clippings, 1951-54 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Publications
      - Information fuer die Frau, 1951-73 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
      - Newsletter by Erna Schlepper, 1957-62 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Information bulletins, 1951, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Lecture series: schedule, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - National election material, 1952-60 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Booklets, 1951-56 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Posters, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 25)